<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vindiciæ Judæorum, or A letter in answer to certain questions propounded by a noble and learned gentleman, touching the reproaches cast on the nation of the Jevves; wherein all objections are candidly, and yet fully cleared. By Rabbi Menasseh Ben Israel a divine and a physician.</title>
            <author>Manasseh ben Israel, 1604-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E.880[1]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 482.b.3[7]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99883420</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99883420</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183673</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183673)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; B1:3[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vindiciæ Judæorum, or A letter in answer to certain questions propounded by a noble and learned gentleman, touching the reproaches cast on the nation of the Jevves; wherein all objections are candidly, and yet fully cleared. By Rabbi Menasseh Ben Israel a divine and a physician.</title>
                  <author>Manasseh ben Israel, 1604-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 41, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R[oger] D[aniel],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 15.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judaism --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183673:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>INDICIAE JUDAEORUM, OR A LETTER In Anſwer to certain Queſtions propounded by a Noble and Learned Gentleman, touching the reproaches caſt on the Nation of the JEVVES; wherein all objections are candidly, and yet fully cleared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Rabbi Menaſſeh Ben Iſrael <hi>a Divine and a Phyſicyan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>R. D.</hi> in the year 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:183673:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183673:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Noble, and Learned Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have received a letter from your worſhip, which was welcome to me; and I read it, becauſe yours, with great delight; if you will pleaſe to allow for the unpleaſantneſſe of the ſubject. For I do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your worſhip, I never met with any thing in my life which I did more deeply reſent, for that it reflecteth upon the credit of a nation, which amongſt ſo many calumnies, ſo manifeſt, (and therefore ſhamefull) I dare to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce innocent. Yet I am afraid, that whilſt I anſwer to them, I ſhall offend ſome, whoſe zeal will not permit them to conſider, that ſelf vindication, as defenſive armes, is naturall to all; but to be wholly ſilent, were to acknowledge what is ſo falſly objected. Wherefore that I may juſtifie my ſelf to my own conſcience, I have obeyed your worſhips commands: for your requeſt muſt not be accounted leſſe, at leaſt by me. I preſume your worſhip cannot expect either prolix, or polite diſcourſes upon ſo ſad a ſubject; for who can be ambitious in his own calamity? I have therefore diſpatcht onely ſome conciſe, and brief relations, bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exceeding the bounds of a letter; yet ſuch as may ſuffice you, to inform the Rulers of the <hi>English</hi> nation, of a truth moſt reall, and ſincere; which I hope they will accept in good part, according to their noble, and ſingular prudence and piety. For innocencie being alwayes moſt free from ſuſpecting evil, I cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that any one hath either ſpoken, or written againſt us, out of any particular hatred that they bare us, but that they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuppoſed our coming might prove prejudiciall to their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and intereſts; charity alwayes beginning at home. Yet notwithſtanding I propounded this matter under an argument of profit (for this hath made us welcome in other countries) and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:183673:3"/>therefore I hope I may prove what I undertake. However, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> but ſmall encouragement to expect the happy attainment of any other deſign, but onely that truth may be juſtified of her children. I ſhall anſwer in order to what your worſhip hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>THE FIRST SECTION.</head>
               <p>ANd in the firſt place, I cannot but weep bitterly, and with much anguiſh of ſoul lament that ſtrange and horrid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation of ſome Chriſtians againſt the diſperſed, and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>Iewes</hi> that dwell among them, when they ſay (what I tremble to write) that the <hi>Iewes</hi> are wont to celebrate the feaſt of unlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened bread, fermenting it with the bloud of ſome Chriſtians, whom they have for this purpoſe killed: when the calumniators themſelves have moſt barbarouſly and cruelly butchered ſome of them. Or to ſpeak more mildly, have found one dead, and caſt the corps, as if it had been murdered by the <hi>Iewes,</hi> into their houſes or yards, as lamentable experience hath proved in ſundry places: and then with unbridled rage and tumult, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the innocent <hi>Iews,</hi> as the committers of this moſt execrable fact. Which deteſtable wickedneſſe hath been ſometimes perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated, that they might thereby take advantage to exerciſe their cruelty upon them; and ſometimes to juſtifie, and patronize their maſſacres already executed. But how farre this accuſation is from any ſemblable appearance of truth, your worſhip may judge by theſe following arguments.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is utterly forbid the <hi>Iewes</hi> to eat any manner of bloud whatſoever, <hi>Levit.</hi> Chapter 7.26. and <hi>Deuter.</hi> 12. where it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>And ye shall eat no manner of bloud,</hi> and in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to this command the <hi>Iewes</hi> eat not the bloud of any ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal. And more then this, if they find one drop of bloud in an egge, they caſt it away as prohibited. And if in eating a piece of bread, it happens to touch any bloud drawn from the teeth, or gummes, it muſt be pared, and cleanſed from the ſaid bloud, as it evidenely appeares in <hi>Sulhan Haruch</hi> and our rituall book. Since then it is thus, how can it enter into any mans heart to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:183673:3"/>that they ſhould eat humane bloud; which is yet more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable, there being ſcarce any nation now remaining upon earth to barbarous, as to commit ſuch wickedneſſe?</p>
               <p n="2">2. The precept in the Decalogue <hi>Thou shalt not kill</hi> is of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall extent; it is a morall command. So that the <hi>Iewes</hi> are bound not onely, not to kill one of thoſe nations where they live, but they are alſo oblig'd by the law of gratitude, to love them. They are the very words of R. <hi>Moſes</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> in <hi>Iad a Razaka,</hi> in his treatiſe of Kings, the tenth Chapter, in the end, <hi>Concerning the nations, the ancients have commanded us to viſit their ſick, and to bury their dead, as the dead of Iſrael, and to relieve, and maintain their poor, as we do the poor of Iſrael, becauſe of the wayes of peace, as it is written, God is good to all, and his tender mercies are over all his works.</hi> Pſal. 145.9. And in conformity hereto, I witneſſe before God bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever, that I have continually ſeen in <hi>Amsterdam</hi> where I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, abundance of good correſpondency, many interchanges of brotherly affection, and ſundry things of reciprocall love. I have thrice ſeen when ſome <hi>Flemine</hi> Chriſtians have fallen into the river in our ward, called <hi>Flemburgh,</hi> our nation caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the river to them, to help them out, and to deliver their lives from death. And certainly he that will thus hazard himſelf to ſave another, cannot harbour ſo much cruell malice, as to kill the innocent, whom he ought out of the duty of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to defend and protect.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is forbidden <hi>Exodus</hi> 21.20. to kill a ſtranger; <hi>If a man ſmite his ſervant, or his maid with a rod, and he die under his hand, he shall ſurely be punished, notwithſtanding, if he continue a day or two, he shall not be punished, for he is his money.</hi> The text ſpeaks of a ſervant that is one of the Gentile nations, becauſe that he onely is ſaid to be the <hi>money</hi> of the <hi>Iew,</hi> who is his maſter, as <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> well notes upon the place. And the Lord commands, that if he die under the hand of his maſter, his maſter ſhall be put to death, for that as it ſeems, he ſtruck him with a murderous intent. But it is otherwiſe if the ſervant dies afterwards, for then it appeares, that he did not ſtrike him with a purpoſe to kill him; for if ſo, he would have killed him out of hand, wherefore he ſhall be free, and it may ſuffice for puniſhment that he hath loſt his money. If therefore a <hi>Iew</hi> cannot
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183673:4"/>kill his ſervant, or ſlave that is one of the nations, according to the law, how much leſſe ſhall he be impowred to murder him that is not his <hi>enemy,</hi> and with whom he leads a quiet and a pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable life? and therefore how can any good man believe that againſt his holy law, a <hi>Iew</hi> (in a ſtrange countrey eſpecially) ſhould make himſelf guilty of ſo execrable a fact?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Admit that it were lawfull (which God forbid) why ſhould they eat the bloud? And ſuppoſing they ſhould eat the bloud, why ſhould they eat it on the Paſſeover? Here at this feaſt, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry confection ought to be ſo pure, as not to admit of any leaven, or any thing that may fermentate, which certainly bloud doth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If the <hi>Iewes</hi> did repute and hold this action (which is never to be named without an epethite of horrour) neceſſary, they would not expoſe themſelves to ſo eminent a danger, to ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and more deſerved puniſhment, unleſſe they were moved to it by ſome divine precept; or at leaſt, ſome conſtitution of their wiſe men. Now we challenge all thoſe men who entertain this dreadfull opinion of us, as obliged in point of juſtice, to cite the place of Scripture, or of the Rabbins, where any ſuch precept, or doctrine is delivered. And untill they do ſo, we will aſſume ſo much liberty, as to conclude it to be no better then a malicious ſlander.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If a man, to ſave his life, may break the Sabbath, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe many of the other commands of the law, as hath been determined in the Talmud; as alſo confirmed by R. <hi>Moſes</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> in the fifth Chapter of his treatiſe of the fundamentalls of the law; yet three are excepted, which are, <hi>idolatry, murther,</hi> and <hi>adultery;</hi> life not being to be purchaſed at ſo dear a rate, as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of theſe heinous ſins: an innocent death being infinitely to be preſerred before it. Wherefore if the killing of a Chriſtian, as they object, were a divine precept, and inſtitution, (which far be it from me to conceive) it were certainly to be null'd and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred void, ſince a man cannot perform it, without indangering his own life; and not onely ſo, but the life of the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of an entire people; and yet more, ſince it is directly a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olation of one of theſe thtee precepts, <hi>Thou shalt do no murder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> which is intended univerſally of all men, as we have ſaid before.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:183673:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>7. The Lord, bleſſed forever, by his prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> Chap. 29.7. gives it in command to the captive Iſraelites that were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed among the heathens, that they ſhould continually pray for, and endeavour the peace, welfare and proſperity of the city wherein they dwelt, and the inhabitants thereof. This the <hi>Iewes</hi> have alwayes done, and continue to this day in all their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, with a particular bleſſing of the Prince or Magiſtrate, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe protection they live. And this the Right Honourable my Lord <hi>St. Iohn</hi> can teſtifie; who when he was Embaſſadour to the Lords the States of the united Provinces, was pleaſed to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our Synagogue at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> with his preſence, where our nation entertained him with muſick, and all expreſſions of joy and gladneſſe, and alſo pronounced a bleſſing, not onely upon his honour, then preſent, but upon the whole Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> for that they were a people in league and amity; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we conceived ſome hopes that they would manifeſt towards us, what we ever bare towards them, <hi>viz.</hi> all love and affection. But to return again to our argument, if we are bound to ſtudy, endeavour, and ſollicite, the good and flouriſhing eſtate of the city where we live, and the inhabitants thereof, how ſhall we then murder their children, who are the greateſt good, and the moſt flouriſhing bleſſing that this life doth indulge to them.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The children of Iſrael are naturally mercifull, and full of compaſſion. This was acknowledged by their enemies, <hi>Kings</hi> 1.20, 31. when <hi>Benhadad</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> was diſcomfited in the battel, and fled away, he became a petitioner for his life to King <hi>Ahab,</hi> who had conquered him; for he underſtood that <hi>the Kings of the houſe of Iſrael were mercifull Kings;</hi> and his own experience confirmed it, when for a little affection that he pretended in a complement, he obtained again his life and fortunes, from which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he event of the warre had diſentitled him. And when the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> made that cruell requeſt to <hi>David,</hi> that ſeven of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſons who were innocent, ſhould be delivered unto them, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>het ſaies, <hi>now the Gibeonites were not of the children of Iſrael,</hi> Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.21, 2. as if he had ſaid, in this cruelty, the piety of the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lites is not ſo much ſet forth, as the tyranny, and implacable rage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Gentiles, the <hi>Gibeonites.</hi> Which being ſo, and experience
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:183673:5"/>withall declares it, <hi>viz.</hi> the fidelity which our nation hath invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably preſerved towards their ſuperiours, then moſt certainly i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is wholly incompatible, and inconſiſtent with the murdering o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their children.</p>
               <p n="9">9. There are ſome Chriſtians, that uſe to inſult againſt the <hi>Iewes</hi> as Chriſtian homicides, that will venter to give a reaſon of theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pretended murtherous practiſes. As if the accuſation were the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt infallibly true, if they can find any ſemblance of a reaſon why it might be ſo. As they ſay, that this is practiſed by them in hatred and deteſtation of Jeſus of Nazareth. And that therefore they ſteal Chriſtian Children, buffeting them in the ſame manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that he was buffetted; thereby to rub up, and revive the memo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of the aforeſaid death. And likewiſe they imagine that the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſecretly ſteal away croſſes, crucifixes, and ſuch like graven images, which Papiſts privately and carefully retein in their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and every day the <hi>Iewes</hi> mainly ſtrike, and buffet, ſhamefully ſpitting on them, with ſuch like ceremonies of deſpight, and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this in hatred of Jeſus. But I admire what they really think, when they object ſuch things as theſe, laying them to our charge. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſurely we cannot believe, that a people, otherwiſe of ſufficient pru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dence, and judgement, can perſwade themſelves into an opinion that the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhould commit ſuch practiſes, unleſſe they could conceive they did them in honour and obedience to the God whom they worſhip. And what kind of obedience is this they perform to God bleſſed for ever, when they directly ſin a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt that ſpeciall command <hi>Thou shalt not kill?</hi> Beſides, this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be committed without the imminent, and manifeſt perill o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their lives and fortunes, and the neceſſary expoſing themſelves to a juſt revenge. Moreover, it is an <hi>Anathema</hi> to a <hi>Iew</hi> to have any graven images in his houſe, or any thing of an idol, which any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the nations figuratively worſhip, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.26.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> p. 532. writes, how that in the year 1240<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>Iewes</hi> circumciſed a Chriſtian child at <hi>Norwich,</hi> and gave him the name <hi>Iurnin,</hi> and reſerved him to be crucified, for which cauſe many of them were moſt cruelly put to death. The truth of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtory will evidently appear upon the conſideration of its citcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. He was firſt circumciſed, and this perfectly conſtitute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:183673:5"/>him a <hi>Iew.</hi> Now for a <hi>Iew</hi> to embrace a Chriſtian in his armes, and foſter him in his boſome, is a teſtimony of great love and affection. But if it was intended that ſhortly after this child ſhould be crucified, to what end was he firſt circumciſed? If it ſhall be ſaid it was out of hatred to the Chriſtians, it appears ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the contrary, that it proceeded from deteſtation of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> or of them who had newly become proſelytes, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the <hi>Iewes</hi> religion. Surely this ſuppoſed pranck (ſtoried to be done in popiſh times) looks more like a piece of the reall ſcene of the Popiſh <hi>Spaniards</hi> piety, who firſt baptiz'd the poor <hi>Indians,</hi> and afterwards out of cruel pity to their ſouls, inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly butchered them; then of ſtrict-law-obſerving <hi>Iewes,</hi> who dare not make a ſport of one of the ſeales of their covenant.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Our captivity under the Mahumetans is farre more bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome, and grievous then under the Chriſtians, and ſo our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients have ſaid, <hi>it is better to inhabit under Edom then Iſmael,</hi> for they are a people more civill, and rationall, and of a better policie, as our nation have found experimentally. For, excepting the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, and better ſort of <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſuch as live in the Court of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> the vulgar people of the <hi>Iewes</hi> that are diſperſed in other countries of the Mahumetan Empire, in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> are treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with abundance of contempt and ſcorn. It would therefore follow, that if this ſacrificing of children be the product and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of hatred, that they ſhould execute and diſgorge it much more upon the Mahumetans, who have reduced them to ſo great calamity and miſery. So that if it be neceſſary to the celebration of the Paſſeover, why do they not as well kill a <hi>Mahumetan?</hi> But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>Iewes</hi> are ſcattered, and diſperſed throughout all thoſe vaſt territories, notwithſtanding all their deſpite againſt us, they never yet to this day forged ſuch a calumnious accuſation, Wherefore it appeares plainly, that it is nothing elſe but a ſlander, and ſuch a one, that conſidering how the ſcene is laid, I cannot ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily determine whether it ſpeak more of malice, or of folly: cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Sultan <hi>Selim</hi> made himſelf very merry with it, when the ſtory was related him by <hi>Moſes Amon</hi> his chief Phyſicyan.</p>
               <p n="12">12. If all that which hath been ſaid is not of ſufficient force to wipe off this accuſation, becauſe the matter on our part is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:183673:6"/>purely negative, and ſo cannot be cleared by evidence of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, I am conſtrained to uſe another way of argument, which the Lord, bleſſed for ever, hath preſcribed <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. which is an oath; wherefore I ſwear, without any deceit or fraud, by the moſt high God, the creatour of heaven and earth, who promulged his law to the people of Iſrael, upon mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> that I never yet to this day ſaw any ſuch cuſtome among the people of Iſrael, and that they doe not hold any ſuch thing by divine precept of the law, or any ordinance or inſtitution of their wiſe men, and that they never committed or endeavoured ſuch wickedneſſe, (that I know, or have credibly heard, or read in any Jewiſh Authours) and if I lie in this matter, then let all the curſes mentioned in <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticus</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> come upon me, let me never ſee the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and conſolations of Zion, nor attain to the reſurrection of the dead. By this I hope I may have proved what I did intend, and certainly this may ſuffice all the friends of truth, and all faithfull Chriſtians to give credit to what I have here averred. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed our adverſaries who have been a little more learned, and conſequently a little more civill then the vulgar, have made a halt at this imputation. <hi>Iohn Hoornbeek</hi> in that book which he lately writ againſt our nation, wherein he hath objected againſt us, right or wrong, all that he could any wayes ſcrape together, was not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding aſhamed to lay this at our door, in his <hi>Prolegomena</hi> pag. 26. where he ſayes, <hi>An autem verum ſit quod vulg ò in hiſtoriis lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c. i.e.</hi> whether that be true which is commonly read in hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to aggravate the <hi>Iewes</hi> hatred againſt the Chriſtians, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Chriſtians againſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that they ſhould annually upon the preparation of the Paſſeover, after a cruell manner ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice a Chriſtian child, privily ſtollen, in diſgrace, and contempt of Chriſt, whoſe paſſion, and crucifixion the Chriſtians celebrate, I will not aſſert for truth; as well knowing, how eaſy it was for thoſe times wherein theſe things are mentioned, to have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, (eſpecially after the Inquiſition was ſet up in the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) to forge, and fain; and how the hiſtories of thoſe ages, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the affection of the writers, were too too much addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and given unto fables and figments. Indeed I have never yet ſeen any of all thoſe relations that hath by any certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183673:6"/>proved this fact, for they are all founded; either upon the uncertain report of the vulgar, or elſe upon the ſecret accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Monks belonging to the inquiſition, not to mention the avarice of the informers, wickedly hanquering after the <hi>Iewes</hi> wealth, and ſo with eaſe forging any wickedneſſe. For in the firſt book of the <hi>Sicilian</hi> conſtitutions tit. 7. we ſee the Emperour <hi>Frederick</hi> ſaying, <hi>Si vero Iudaeus, vel Saracenus ſit, in quibus prout certò perpendimus Chriſtiano cum perſecutio minus abundat ad praeſens,</hi> but if he be a <hi>Iew</hi> or a <hi>Saracen,</hi> againſt whom, as we have weighed, the perſecution of the Chriſtians do much abound, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thus taxing the violence of certain Chriſtians againſt the <hi>Iewes.</hi> Or if perhaps it hath ſometimes happened, that a Chriſtian was kill'd by a <hi>Iew,</hi> we muſt not therefore ſay that in all places where they inhabit, they annually kill a Chriſtian Child. And for that which <hi>Thomas Cantipratenſis</hi> lib. 2. cap. 23. affirms, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is certainly known, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> every year, in every province, caſt lots what city or town ſhall afford Chriſtian bloud to the other cities. I can give it no more credit then his other fictions and lies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath ſtuffed his book. Thus farre <hi>Iohn Hoornbeek.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Notwithſtanding all this, there are not wanting ſome hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, that relate theſe and the like calumnies againſt an afflicted people, For which cauſe the Lord ſaith, <hi>He that toucheth you touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the apple of my eye,</hi> Zach. 2.6. I ſhall curſolarily mention ſome paſſages that have occurred in my time, whereof, I ſay not that I was an eye witneſſe, but onely that they were of generall report and credence, without the leaſt contradiction. I have faithfully noted both the names of the perſons, the places where, and the time when they happened, in my continuation of <hi>Flavius Joſephus,</hi> I ſhall be the leſſe curious therefore in reciting them here. In <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi> the Metropolis of <hi>Auſtria, Frederick</hi> being Emperour, there was a pond frozen, according to the cold of thoſe parts, wherein three boyes (as it too frequently happens) were drowned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when they were miſſed, the imputation is caſt upon the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and they are incontinently indicted, for murthering of them, to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate their Paſſeover. And being impriſoned, after infinite pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſupplications made to no effect, three hundred of them were burnt, when the pond thawd, theſe three boyes were found,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:183673:7"/>and then their innocency was clearly evinc'd although too late after the execution of this cruelty.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Araguza</hi> about thirty yeares ago, there was a Chriſtian wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, into whoſe houſe there came a little girle (of eleven yeares of age, daughter to a neighbouring gentleman) richly adorned with jewels: this wretched woman, not thinking of a ſafer way to rob her, then by killing her, cut her throat, and hid her under her bed, the girle was preſently miſt, and by information they underſtood that ſhe was ſeen to go into that houſe, they call a Magiſtrate to ſearch the houſe, and find the girle dead, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the fact, and as if ſhe ſhould have expiated her own guilt by deſtroying a <hi>Iew,</hi> though never ſo innocent, ſhe ſaid, ſhe did it at the inſtigation and perſwaſion of one <hi>Iſaac Jeshurun,</hi> for that the <hi>Jewes</hi> wanted bloud to celebrate their feaſt: ſhe was hang'd, and the <hi>Jew</hi> was apprehended, who being ſix times cruelly tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd, they employing their wits in inventing unheard of, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable torments, ſuch as might gain <hi>Perillous</hi> the eſtimation of mercifull and compaſſionate, ſtill cryes out of the falſhood of the accuſation, ſaying, that that wickedneſſe which he never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, no not ſo much as in his dreams, was maliciouſly imputed to him, yet notwithſtanding he was condemned to remain cloſe priſoner for twenty yeares, (though he continued there onely three,) and to be fed there through a trough, upon the bread and water of affliction, being cloſe manacled, and naked, within a four ſquare wall, built for that purpoſe, that he might there periſh in his own dung. This mans brother <hi>Joſeph Jeshurun</hi> is now living at this time in <hi>Hamborough.</hi> This miſerable man calling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, beſeeching him to ſhew ſome ſignall teſtimony of his innocencie, and citing before his divine tribunall the Senatours who had with no more mercy, then juſtice, thus grievouſly and inhumanely afflicted him; the bleſſed God was a juſt Judge, for the Prince died ſuddenly at a banquet, the Sunday next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing the giving of the ſentence, and during the time of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, the aforeſaid Senatours by little and little dropt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and died, which was prudently obſerved by thoſe few that yet remain'd, wherefore they reſolved to deliver themſelves by reſtoring him to his liberty, accounting it as a particular di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:183673:7"/>providence: this man came out well, paſſed throughout all <hi>Italy,</hi> where he was ſeen, to the admiration of all that had cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of his ſufferings, and died a few yeares ſince at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. The act of the faith (which is ordinarily done at <hi>Toledo</hi>) was done at <hi>Madrid, Anno</hi> 1632. in the preſence of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> where the Inquiſitors did then take an oath of the King and queen, that they ſhould maintain and conſerve the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick faith in their dominions. In this act it is found printed, how that a family of our nation was burnt, for confeſſing upon the wrack the truth of a certain accuſation of a maid ſervant, who, (provoked out of ſome diſguſt) ſaid, that they had ſcourged, and whip't an image, which by the frequent laſhes, iſſued forth a great deal of bloud, and crying with an out ſtretched voice, ſaid unto them, why do you thus cruelly ſcourge me? the whole no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility well underſtood that it was all falſe, but things of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition all muſt huſh.</p>
               <p n="15">15. A very true ſtory happened at <hi>Lisbon, Anno</hi> 1631. A certain Church miſſed one night a ſilver pixe or box, wherein was the popiſh hoſts. And foraſmuch as they had ſeen a young youth of our nation, whoſe name was <hi>Simao pires ſolis,</hi> ſufficiently noble, to paſſe by the ſame night, not farre from thence, who went to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit a Lady, he was apprehended, impriſoned, and terribly tortured. They cut off his hands, and after they had dragged him along the ſtreets, burnt him. one year paſſed over, and a thief at the foot of the gallowes confeſſed how he himſelf had rifled and plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſhrine of the hoſt, and not that poor innocent whom they had burnt. This young mans brother was a Frier, a great Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſt, and a preacher, he lives now a <hi>Jew</hi> in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and calls himſelf <hi>Eliazar de ſolis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. Some perhaps will ſay, that men are not blame worthy for imputing to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that which they themſelves with their own mouthes have confeſt. But ſurely he hath little underſtanding of wracks, and tortures that ſpeaks thus. An Earle of <hi>Portugal,</hi> when his Phyſicyan was impriſoned for being a <hi>Jew,</hi> requeſted one of the inquiſitors, by letter, that he would cauſe him to be ſet at liberty, for that he knew for certain that he was a very good Chriſtian, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183673:8"/>he not being able to undergo the tortures inflicted on him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed himſelf a <hi>Iew,</hi> and became a penitentiary. At which the Earl being much incenſt, feins himſelf ſick, and deſires the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitor by one of his ſervants, that he would be pleaſed to come and viſit him. when he came, he commanded him that he ſhould confeſſe that himſelf was a <hi>Iew,</hi> and further, that he ſhould put it down in writing with his own hand, which when he refuſed to do, he charges ſome of his ſervants to put a helmet that was red hot in the fire, (provided for this purpoſe) upon his head; at which, he not being able to endure this threatned torment, takes him aſide to confeſſe, and alſo he writ with his own hand that he was a <hi>Iew:</hi> whereupon the Earl takes occaſion to reprove his injuſtice, cruelty, and inhumanity, ſaying, in like manner as you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, did my Phyſicyan confeſſe. Beſides that, you have preſently, onely out of fear, not ſence of torment, confeſt more. For this cauſe in the Iſraelitiſh Senate, no torture was ever infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, but onely every perſon was convicted at the teſtimony of two witneſſes. That ſuch like inſtruments of cruelty may enforce children that have been tenderly educated, and fathers that have lived deliciouſly to confeſſe that they have whipt an image, and been guilty of ſuch like criminall offences, daily experience may demonſtrate.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Others will perchance alledge, theſe are hiſtories indeed, but they are not ſacred, nor canonicall. I anſwer, Love and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred ſayes <hi>Plutarch,</hi> corrupt the truth of every thing, as experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſufficiently declares it; when we ſee that which comes to paſſe, that one and the ſame thing, in one and the ſame city, at one and the ſame time, is related in different manners. I my ſelf in my own Negotiation here have found it. For it hath been ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured abroad, that our nation had purchaſed S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church for to make it their Synagogue, notwithſtanding that it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a temple conſecrated to the worſhip of <hi>Diana.</hi> And many other things have been reported of us that never entred into the thoughts of our nation; as I have ſeen a fabulous Narrative of the proceedings of a great Council of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> aſſembled in the plain of <hi>Ageda</hi> in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> to determine whether the Meſſiah were come or no.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:183673:8"/>18. And now, ſince that it is evident that it is forbidden the <hi>Iewes</hi> to eat any manner of bloud, and that to kill a man is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prohibited by our law, and the reaſons before given are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaneous and agreeable to every ones underſtanding, I know it will be inquired by many, but eſpecially by thoſe who are more pious, and the friends of truth, how this calumnie did ariſe, and from whence it derived its firſt originall. I may anſwer, that this wickedneſſe is laid to their charge for divers reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Ruffinus</hi> the familiar friend of S. <hi>Hierome</hi> in his verſion of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> his ſecond book that he writ againſt <hi>Apion</hi> the Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian (for the Greek text is there wanting) tells us how <hi>Apion</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented this ſlander to gratifie <hi>Antiochus,</hi> to excuſe his ſacriledge, and juſtifie his perfidious dealing with the <hi>Iewes,</hi> making their eſtates ſupply his wants. <hi>Prophet a vero aliorum est Apion</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Apion</hi> is become a Prophet, and ſaid that <hi>Antiochus</hi> found in the temple, a bed, with a man lying upon it, and a table ſet before him, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all dainties both of ſea and land, and fowles, and that this man was aſtoniſhed at them, and preſently adores the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the King, as coming to ſuccour and relieve him, and proſtrating himſelf at his knees, &amp; ſtretching out his right hand, he implores liberty; whreat the King commanding him to ſit down and declare who he was, why he dwelt there, and what was the cauſe of this his plentifull proviſion? the man with ſighs and tears; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably weeps out his neceſſity: and tells him that he is a <hi>Grecian,</hi> and whilſt he travelled about the province to get food, he was ſuddenly apprehended, and caught up by ſome ſtrange men, and brought to the temple, and there ſhut up, that he might be ſeen by no man, but be there fatted with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of dainties, and that theſe unexpected benefits wrought in him at the firſt joy, then ſuſpicion, after that aſtoniſhment, and laſt of all, adviſing with the Miniſter that came unto him, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that the <hi>Iewes</hi> every year, at a certain time appointed according to their ſecret and <hi>ineffable</hi> law, take up ſome Greek ſtranger, and after he hath been fed delicately for the ſpace of a whole year, they bring him into a certain wood, and kill him. Then according to their ſolem rites and ceremonies, they ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice his body, and every one taſting of his intrails, in the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:183673:9"/>up of this Greek they enter into a ſolemn oath, that they will bear an immortall feude and hatred to the Greeks. And then they caſt the reliques of this periſhing man into a certain pit. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this <hi>Apion</hi> makes him to ſay, that onely ſome few dayes remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, before his execution, &amp; to deſire the King that he, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and worſhipping the Grecian gods, would revenge the bloud of his ſubjects upon the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and deliver him from his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching death. This fable (ſaith <hi>Ioſephus</hi>) as it is moſt full of all tragedy, ſo it abounds with cruell impudence, I had rather you ſhould read the confutation of this ſlander there, then I to write it in this place, you will find it in the <hi>Geneva</hi> edition of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus,</hi> pag. 1066.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The very ſame accuſation and horrid wickedneſſe of killing children, and eating their bloud, was of old by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient heathens, charg'd upon the Chriſtians, that thereby they might make them odious, and incenſe the common people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as appeares by <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>Apologia contra gentes, Iuſtin Martyr in apologia</hi> 2. <hi>ad Anton. Euſebius Caeſareenſis</hi> l. 5. cap. 1. &amp; 4. <hi>Pineda</hi> in his <hi>Monarchia Eccleſiaſtica</hi> l. 11. c. 52: and many others, as is known ſufficiently. So that the imputation of this cruelty, which as to them continues onely in memory, is to the very ſame purpoſe, at this day charged upon the <hi>Iewes.</hi> And as they deny this fact, as being falſly charged upon them, ſo in like manner do we deny it, and I may ſay perhaps with a little more reaſon, foraſmuch as we eat not any manner of bloud, wherein they do not think themſelves obliged.</p>
               <p>Now the reaſon of this ſlander was alwayes the <hi>covetous ambition</hi> of ſome, who deſiring to gain their wealth, and poſſeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their eſtates, have forg'd and introduc'd this enormous accuſation, to colour their wickedneſſe, under a ſpecious pretence of revenging their own bloud. And to this purpoſe, I remember that when I reproved a Rabbi (who came out of <hi>Poland</hi> to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi>) for the exceſſe of uſurie in <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> which they exacted of the Chriſtians, and told him how moderate they in <hi>Holland</hi> and in <hi>Italy</hi> were, he replyed, we are of neceſſity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to do ſo, becauſe they ſo often raiſe up falſe witneſſes againſt us, and levie more from us at once, then we are able to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183673:9"/>get again by them in many yeares. And ſo, as experience ſhews, it uſually ſucceeds with our poor people under this pretext and colour.</p>
               <p n="19">19. And ſo it hath been divers times; men miſchieving the <hi>Iewes</hi> to excuſe their own wickedneſſe; as to inſtance one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent in the time of a certain King of <hi>Portugal.</hi> The Lord, bleſſed for ever, took away his ſleep one night, (as he did from King <hi>Ahashuer us</hi>) and he went up into a belcony in the palace, from whence he could diſcover the whole city, and from thence (the moon ſhining clear) he eſpyed two men carrying a dead corps, which they caſt into a <hi>Iew's</hi> yard. He preſently diſpatches a couple of ſervants, and commands them, yet with a ſeeming care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, they ſhould trace and follow thoſe men, and take notice of their houſe; which they accordingly did. The next day there is a hurly burly and a tumult in the city, accuſing the <hi>Iewes</hi> of murder. Thereupon the King apprehends theſe rogues, and they confeſſe the truth; and conſidering that this buſineſſe was guided by a particular divine providence, calls ſome of the wiſe men of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and asks them how they tranſlate the 4. verſe of the 121 Pſalm, and they anſwered, <hi>Behold, he that keepeth Iſrael will neither ſlumber nor ſleep.</hi> The King replied, if he will not ſlumber then much leſſe will he ſleep; you do not ſay well, for the true tranſlation is, <hi>Behold, the Lord doth not ſlumber, neither will he ſuffer him that keepeth Iſrael to ſleep.</hi> God who hath yet a care over you, hath taken away my ſleep, that I might be an eye witneſſe of that wickedneſſe which is this day laid to your charge. This with many ſuch like relations we may read in the book called <hi>Scebet Iehuda,</hi> how ſundry times, when our nation was at the very brink of deſtruction, for ſuch forged ſlanders, the truth hath diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf for their deliverance.</p>
               <p n="20">20. This matter of bloud hath been heretofore diſcuſſed and diſputed before one of the Popes, at a full councell; where it was determined to be nothing elſe but a mere calumnie: and hereupon gave liberty to the <hi>Iewes</hi> to dwell in his countryes, and gave the princes of <hi>Italy</hi> to underſtand the ſame, as alſo <hi>Alfonſo</hi> the wiſe King of <hi>Spain.</hi> And ſuppoſe any one man had done ſuch a thing, as I believe never any <hi>Iew</hi> did ſo, yet this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:183673:10"/>were great cruelty to puniſh a whole nation for one mans wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p n="21">21. But why ſhould I uſe more words about this matter, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that is come upon us, was foretold by all the prophets? <hi>Moſes Deut.</hi> 28.61. <hi>Moreover, every ſickneſſe and every plague which is not written in the book of this law, them will the Lord bring upon thee, &amp;c. becauſe thou haſt not hearkned to the voice of the Lord thy God. David</hi> in the 44. Pſalm makes a dolefull complaint of thoſe evils, and ignominious reproaches, wherewith we are invironed round about in this captivity, as if we were the proper center of miſery, ſaying, <hi>For thy ſake are we killed all the day long, we are counted as sheep for the ſlaughter.</hi> The ſame he ſpeaks Pſalm 74. and in other Pſalms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ezekiel</hi> more particularly mentions this calumnie; God, bleſ-for ever, promiſing Chap. 36.13. that in time to come the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring of men, or the eating of mans bloud ſhall be no more imputed to them, according to the true and proper expoſition of the learned <hi>Don Iſaac Abarbanel.</hi> The bleſſed God, according to the multitude of his mercies, will have compaſſion upon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and will take away the reproach of Iſrael from off the earth, that it may be no more heard, as is propheſied by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and let this ſuffice to have ſpoken as to this point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>THE SECOND SECTION.</head>
               <p>YOur worſhip deſired joyntly, to know what ceremony, or humiliation the <hi>Iewes</hi> uſe in their Synagogues, toward the book of the Law; for which they are by ſome igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly reputed to be idolaters. I ſhall anſwer it in Order.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the <hi>Iewes</hi> hold themſelves bound to ſtand up when the book of the Law written upon parchment, is taken out of the desk, utill it is opened on the pulpit, to ſhew it to the people, and afterwards to be read. We ſee that obſerved in <hi>Nehemias,</hi> cap. 8.6. where it is ſaid, <hi>And when he had opened it, all the people ſtood up.</hi> and this they do in reverence to the word of God, and that ſacred Book.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:183673:10"/>For the ſame cauſe, when it paſſeth from the desk toward the pulpit, all that it paſſeth by, bow down their heads a little, with reverence; which can be no idolatry for theſe following reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is one thing <hi>adorare, viz.</hi> to <hi>adore,</hi> and another <hi>venerari, viz.</hi> to <hi>worship.</hi> For <hi>Adoration</hi> is forbidden to any creature, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angelicall, or Earthly; but <hi>Worship</hi> may be given to either of them, as to men of a higher rank, commonly ſtiled <hi>worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> And ſo <hi>Abraham,</hi> who in his time rooted out vain idolatry, humbled himſelf, and alſo proſtrated himſelf before thoſe three gueſts, which then he entertained for <hi>Men.</hi> As alſo <hi>Ioſuah</hi> the holy Captain of the people, did proſtrate himſelf to another Angel, which with a ſword in his hand, made him afraid, at the gates of <hi>Iericho.</hi> Wherefore if thoſe were juſt men, and if we are obliged to follow their example, and they were not reprehended for it, it is clear, that to worſhip the Law in this manner as we do, can be no idolatry.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The <hi>Iewes</hi> are very ſcrupulous in ſuch things, and and fear in the leaſt, to <hi>appear</hi> to give any honour or reverence to images. And ſo it is to be ſeen in the <hi>Talmud,</hi> and in R. <hi>Moſes</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> in his Treatiſe of idolatry: That if by chance any Iſraelite ſhould paſſe by a Church, that had images on the out ſide, and at that time a thorn ſhould run into his foot, he may not ſtoop to pull it out, becauſe he that ſhould ſee him, might ſuſpect he bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſuch an image. Therefore according to this ſtrictneſſe, if that were any appearance of idolatry to bow to the Law, the <hi>Iewes</hi> would utterly abhorre it; and ſince they do it, it is an evident ſign that it is none.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to <hi>kiſſe images</hi> is the principall worſhip of idolatry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as God ſaith, in the 1 of <hi>Kings</hi> 19.19. <hi>Yet</hi> I <hi>have left me ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in Iſrael, all the knees that have not bowed unto Baal, and every mouth that hath not kiſſed him.</hi> But if that were ſo, it would follow, that all men, who kiſſe the Teſtament after they are ſworn, ſhould be idolaters. But becauſe that is not ſo, ſince that act is but a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple worſhip, by the ſame reaſon it will follow, that to bow the head, cannot be reputed for idolatry.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Experience ſheweth, that in all Nations the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:183673:11"/>that men uſe mutually one towards another, is to bow the head: And alſo there are degrees thereof, according to the quality of the perſon with whom they ſpeak; which ſhew that in the opinion of all nations, it is no idolatry, and therefore much leſſe, to reverence the Law with bowing of the body.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, In <hi>Aſia</hi> (and it is the ſame almoſt in all the world) the people receiving a decree, or order of the king, they take it, and kiſſe it, and ſet it upon the head. We owe much more to Gods word, and to his divine Commandments.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>Ptolomeus Philadelphus,</hi> receiving the 72 <hi>Interpreters</hi> with the book of the Law, into his preſence, he roſe from his ſeat, and proſtrating himſelf ſeven times, worſhipped it, (as <hi>Ariſtaeus</hi> aſſures us.) If a Gentile did this to a law which he thought did not oblige him, much more do we owe reverence to that Law which was particularly given unto us.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> hold for the Articles of their Faith, that there is a God; who is one in moſt ſimple unity; eternall, incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall; who gave the written Law unto his people Iſrael, by the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prince, and chief of all the Prophets; whoſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence takes care for the world which he created; who takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of all mens works, and rewardeth or puniſheth them. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that one day <hi>Meſsias</hi> ſhall come to gather together the ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Iſraelites, and ſhortly after ſhall be the reſurrection of the dead.</p>
               <p>Theſe are their Doctrines, which I believe contain not any idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; nor yet in the opinion of thoſe that are of other judgements; For, as a moſt learned Chriſtian of our time hath written, in a French book, which he calleth the <hi>Rappel</hi> of the <hi>Iewes</hi> (in which he makes the King of <hi>France</hi> to be their leader, when they ſhall return to their country,) the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſaith he, ſhall be ſaved, for yet we expect a <hi>ſecond</hi> coming of the ſame <hi>Meſsias;</hi> and the <hi>Iewes</hi> believe that that coming is the <hi>first,</hi> and not the ſecond, and by that faith they ſhall be ſaved; for the difference conſiſts onely in the circumſtance of the time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:183673:11"/>
               <head>THE THIRD SECTION.</head>
               <p>SIr, I hope I have given ſatisfaction to your worſhip, touching thoſe points. I ſhall yet further inform you with the ſame ſincerity, concerning the reſt. <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> in his <hi>Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaeca,</hi> lib. 2. <hi>Titulo contra Talmud,</hi> and others, as <hi>Biatenſis, Ordine</hi> 1. <hi>Tract.</hi> 1. <hi>Titulo</hi> Perachot. averre out of the <hi>Talmud.</hi> cap. 4. <q>that every <hi>Iew,</hi> thrice a day, curſeth all Chriſtians, and prayeth to God to confound, and root them out, with their Kings and Princes. And this is eſpecially done in the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> by the <hi>Iewes</hi> Prieſts, thrice a day.</q> I pray let ſuch as love the truth, ſee the <hi>Talmud,</hi> in the quoted place; and they ſhall find nothing of that which is objected: onely there is recited in the ſaid fourth Chapter, the daily prayer, which ſpeaks of <hi>Minim,</hi> that is, <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, ordained</hi> in <hi>Tabne,</hi> (that is a town not farre from <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> between <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Gazim,</hi> &amp;c.) the Talmud hath no more. Hence <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> by diſtillation, draws forth the foreſaid ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnie, when as, what the <hi>Talmud</hi> rehearſeth briefly, to be made onely by the wiſe men in the ſaid Town, he ſaith, was a conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the <hi>Talmud</hi> long after.</p>
               <p>Now let us ſee what was done by thoſe wiſe men in the ſaid Town; and let us examine, whether that may juſtly offend the Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>There is in the daily prayers a certain Chapter where it is thus written, <hi>la-Mumarim,</hi> &amp;c. that is, <hi>For Apostates, let there be no hope, let all Hereticks be deſtroyed, and all thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and all that hate thee, let them perish. And thou shalt root out the kingdome of pride forthwith, weaken, and put it out, and in our dayes.</hi> This whole Chapter ſpeaketh nothing of Chriſtians originally, but of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who fell in thoſe times, to the <hi>Zaduces,</hi> and <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureans,</hi> and to the Gentiles, as <hi>Moſes</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſaith, Tract. <hi>Tephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</hi> cap. 2. For by Apoſtates and Hereticks are not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood all men, that are of a diverſe religion, or heathens, or Gentiles, but thoſe renegado <hi>Iewes,</hi> who did abrogate the whole
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:183673:12"/>Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or any Articles received thence; and ſuch are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly by us called <hi>Hereticks.</hi> For according to the Law of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, he is not properly an Apoſtate, or Heritick, who is origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally bred a ſcholler and a candid follower from his youth of a diverſe law, and ſo continueth: otherwiſe native <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Haga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> and other Nations that are no Chriſtians, nor ever were ſhould be be properly called Apoſtates, and Hereticks in reſpect of Chriſtians; which is abſurd, as it is abſurd for the <hi>Iewes</hi> to call the Chriſtians Apoſtates, or Hereticks. Wherefore it ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing of Chriſtians, but of the fugitive <hi>Iewes,</hi> that is, ſuch as have deſerted the ſtandard, or the ſacred Law.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Laſtly, neither the kingdomes, nor kings that are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or <hi>Hagarens,</hi> or followers of other Sects are curſed here, but namely the kingdome of Pride. Certain it is that in that time (wherein, our wiſe men added to the daily Prayers the foreſaid Chapter) there was no kingdome of Chriſtians. what therefore that kingdome of pride was, ſhould any man ask, who can plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew it? So much as we can conjecture by it, it is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>Romans</hi> which then flouriſhed, which did rule over all Nations tyrannically and proudly, eſpecially over the <hi>Iewes.</hi> For, after that, <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> with his ſon <hi>Titus,</hi> had diſſipated all <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea.</hi> And though ſom <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours after that became Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or had a good opinion of Chriſtianity, yet the kingdome of the <hi>Romans</hi> was heatheniſh, and without diſtinction, was proud, and tyrannicall And however the <hi>Iewes</hi> repeated the ſame words of the prayer when the Prince was very good, and they lived un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a juſt government, that they did, onely of an ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, without any malice to the preſent government. And now truly in all their books printed again, the foreſaid words are want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, leſt they ſhould now be unjuſtly objected againſt the <hi>Iewes;</hi> and ſo for <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> they ſay, <hi>ſecret accuſers, or betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of the <hi>Iewes.</hi> And for the <hi>kingdome of pride,</hi> they ſubſtitute <hi>all Zedim,</hi> that is, <hi>proud men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. After this manner, to avoid ſcandall, did the 72 Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, who coming in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> to unclean beaſts; in the place of <hi>Arnebeth</hi> which ſignifies the <hi>Hare,</hi> they put <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>rough foot;</hi> leaving the Name, and keeping the ſenſe. They would
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:183673:12"/>not retein the Hebrew word <hi>Arnebeth,</hi> as they have done in ſome other appellatives, leſt the wife of <hi>Ptolomy</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Arne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet,</hi> ſhould think that the <hi>Iewes</hi> had mocked her, if they ſhould have placed her name amongſt the unclean beaſts. Neither would they render it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>lagoon,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>lagon,</hi> which in the Greek lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſignifies a <hi>Hare,</hi> leſt <hi>Ptolomy</hi> himſelf who was the ſon, and nephew of the <hi>Lagi,</hi> ſhould be offended, to ſee the name of his family regiſtred among the creatures that were unclean. Beſides, <hi>Plutarch</hi> records, how that it was deeply reſented, as a very high affront, and contempt, when one asked <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> who was <hi>Lagus</hi> his father, as if it ſcoffingly reflected upon his obſcure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction and deſcent.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The very like calumnie fell out concerning the very ſame Chapter of our Prayer, when <hi>Mulet Zidan</hi> reigned in <hi>Morocco.</hi> A certain fugive <hi>Iew,</hi> to ſhew himſelf conſtant in the Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Religion, and an enemy to his own Nation, accuſed the <hi>Iewes</hi> before this king, ſaying, that they prayed to God for his deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, when they mention in their prayers all <hi>Zedim,</hi> as though they would have all the Family of <hi>Zidan</hi> deſtroyed. They excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves with the truth, and affirmed, in praying againſt <hi>Zedim,</hi> that they prayed onely againſt <hi>proud men,</hi> (as that word in their Hebrew language properly ſignifieth) and not againſt his Majeſty. The King admitted of their excuſe; but ſaid unto them, that becauſe of the equivocation of the word, they ſhould change it for another.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For certain, the <hi>Iewes</hi> give no occaſion, that any Prince, or Magiſtrate ſhould be offended with them; but contrariwiſe, as it ſeems to me, they are bound to love them, to defend, and protect them. For, by their <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Talmud,</hi> and the inviolable <hi>cuſtome</hi> of the diſperſed <hi>Iewes,</hi> every where, upon every Sabbath day, and in all yearly ſolemnities, they have prayers for Kings and Princes, under whoſe Government the <hi>Iewes</hi> live, be they Chriſtians, or of other Religions, I ſay by their <hi>Law,</hi> as <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> ch. 29. commandeth, <hi>viz. Seek ye the peace of the city, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> I <hi>have cauſed you to be carried away captives, and pray for them, unto the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. By the <hi>Talmud</hi> ord. 4. Tract. 4. <hi>Abodazara.</hi> cap. 1. <hi>there is a prayer for the peace of the Kingdome,</hi> from <hi>cuſtome,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:183673:13"/>never intermitted of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> Whereſoever they are on the Sabbath day, and their annuall ſolemnities, the Miniſter of the Synagogue before he bleſſeth the people of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> doth with a loud voice, bleſſe the Prince of the country under whom they live, that all the <hi>Iewes</hi> may hear it; and they ſay Amen. You have ſeen the Form of the prayer in the book entitled The hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Addreſſes.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In like manner the ancients obſerve, that whereas God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands in <hi>Numbers</hi> 29.13. that ſeventy bullocks ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed upon the ſeven dayes of the feaſt of tabernacles, that this was in reſpect of the ſeventy nations (who ſhall one day come up to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> year after year, to keep this feaſt of tabernacles, <hi>Zechar.</hi> 14.16.) for whoſe conſervation they alſo ſacrificed. For they ſay, that <hi>all the nations of the earth shall be bleſſed in Abraham, and in his ſeed, not onely ſpiritually, and in the knowledge of the one firſt cauſe, but alſo that at this time they shall enjoy temporall, and earthly bleſsings, by vertue of that promiſe.</hi> And ſo in the time of the ſecond temple, they offered up ſacrifice for their confederate nations, as may appear by theſe enſuing inſtances.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Megilat Tahanit.</hi> cap. 9. it is reported, that when <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, at the inſtigation of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> that inhabited mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> went with a reſolution to deſtroy the temple, <hi>Simeon</hi> the juſt met him in the way, and amongſt divers reaſons that he urged to divert him from his purpoſe, told him, <hi>this is the place, where we pray unto God for the welfare of your ſelf, and of your kingdome, that it may not be deſtroyed, and shall theſe men perſwade you to deſtroy this place?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like we find in the firſt book of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> cap. 7.33. and in <hi>Ioſephus</hi> his Antiq. <hi>lib.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. when <hi>Demetrius</hi> had ſent <hi>Nicanor</hi> the Generall of his army againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Prieſts, with the Elders of the people went forth to ſalute him, and to ſhew him the ſacrifice which they offered up to God for the welfare of the King.</p>
               <p>In the ſame hiſtory <hi>lib.</hi> 2.3. and in <hi>Joſephus Gorionides</hi> lib. 3. cap. 16. we may read, that <hi>Heliodorus</hi> Generall to <hi>Selencus,</hi> came to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with the ſame intent, <hi>Onias</hi> the High-prieſt, beſought him, not to deſtroy that place, where they prayed to God for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:183673:13"/>the proſperity of the King, and his iſſue, and for the conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his kingdome.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Chapter of <hi>Baruch,</hi> the diſciple of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> we find that the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who were firſt carried captive into <hi>Babylon</hi> with <hi>Iechonias,</hi> made a collection of money, according to every ones power, and ſent it to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Behold, we have ſent you money, wherewith ye shall buy offerings, and pray for the life of Nebuchadnezzar, and for the life of Baltaſar his ſonne, that their dayes may be upon earth as the dayes of heaven, and that God would give us ſtrength, and lighten our eyes, that we may live under their shadow, that we may long do them ſervice, and find favour in their ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Aſia</hi> did the ſame, as is reported by <hi>Joſephus Gori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onides,</hi> lib. 3. cap. 4. they ſent letters, with a preſent to <hi>Hircanus</hi> the High-prieſt, deſiring that prayers might be made for the life of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> and his companion <hi>Marcus Antonius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philo Judaeus,</hi> in the book of his Embaſſage to <hi>Caius,</hi> making mention of a letter which <hi>Caius</hi> ſent, requiring his ſtatue to be ſet up in the ſacred temple, and <hi>Agrippa's</hi> anſwer thereupon, unto the ſaid Emperour, reports, that there were theſe words in it, <hi>viz. The Iewes ſacrifice for the proſperity of your Empire, and that not onely upon their ſolemn feaſts, but alſo every day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like is recorded by <hi>Joſephus,</hi> (lib. 2. cap. 9. <hi>De bello Judaico</hi>) the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Petronius</hi> Generall to the Emperour <hi>Caius,</hi> we <hi>daily offer up burnt offerings unto God, for the peace of the Emperour, and the whole people of Rome.</hi> And in his ſecond book againſt <hi>Api<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> he ſayes, <hi>we Hebrews have allwayes accuſtomed to honour Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours with particular ſacrifices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither was this ſervice ever entertained unthankfully, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the decree of <hi>Cyrus, Ezra</hi> 6.3. where alſo <hi>Darius</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, that <hi>of the Kings goods, even of the tribute, expences should be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orth-with given unto the Elders of the Iewes</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and that which they had need of, both young bullocks, and rammes, and lambs for the burnt-offerings of the Lord of heaven, and wheat, ſalt, wine; and oyl,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that they might offer ſacrifices of a ſweet ſavour, unto the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the King, and of his ſonnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame alſo was commanded afterwards by <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> who alſo conferred liberally many large gifts, as well towards the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:183673:14"/>building of the temple, as the maintaining of the ſacrifices. As for <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, he lighted down out of his chariot, and bowed himſelf at the feet of the High-prieſt, deſiring him to offer up ſacrifice to God on his behalf. And who can be ignorant of <hi>Ptolomy Philadelphus,</hi> how richly he endowed the temple, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by <hi>Ariſteas?</hi> Nor did <hi>Antiochus</hi> king of the <hi>Greeks</hi> unlike this, when by a publick edict, he forbid <hi>that any ſtranger should enter the temple, to prophane that place, which the Hebrews had conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to religion, and divine worship.</hi> (Joſephus <hi>lib.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.) <hi>Demetrius</hi> did the like, (<hi>Joſephus</hi> lib. 13. cap. 5.6. To which may be added, that when they of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> contended with them of <hi>Samaria,</hi> about the honour and dignity of the temple, before <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, the <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> Prieſt in his plea, urged, <hi>that this temple was ever had in great reverenee by all the Kings of</hi> Aſia, <hi>and by them enricht with ſundry ſplendid and magnificent gifts.</hi> In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond book of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> againſt <hi>Apion,</hi> we read, that <hi>Ptolomy Euerge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> when he had conquered <hi>Syria,</hi> offered up <hi>Euchariſticall ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> not to idols, and falſe Gods, but to the true God, at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> according to the manner of the <hi>Iewes. Pompey</hi> the great, as is mentioned by <hi>Ioſephus de bello Iudaico</hi> (lib. 1. cap. 5.) durſt not ſpoyl, no nor ſo much as touch the treaſures of the temple, not becauſe (as <hi>Tully</hi> in his Oration for <hi>Plancius</hi> ſuppoſeth, to whom <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his book <hi>de civitate Dei aſſentos</hi>) he feared leſt he might be thought too avaritious; for this ſeems in compariſon, very ridiculous, and childiſh; for military law would ſoon have acquitted him for this; but becauſe of the reverence to the place with which his mind was ſo affected. <hi>Philo Iudaeus,</hi> (p. 102. 6.) relates a letter of <hi>Agrippa's,</hi> where he writes, that <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> had the temple in ſo great reverence, that he commanded a ſacrifice of one bullock, and two lambs, to be offered up every day out of his own revenues. And his wife <hi>Iulia Auguſta,</hi> adorn'd it with golden cups, and baſons, and many other coſtly gifts. Neither did <hi>Cleopatra</hi> Queen of <hi>Egypt,</hi> fall ſhort of her liberallity. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> throughout the 22 years of his Empire, commanded ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices to be offered up unto God, out of his own tribute. The like did <hi>Nero,</hi> till the unadviſed raſhneſſe of <hi>Eleazar</hi> in refuſing his ſacrifice, alienated the mind of the Emperour, that he became the cauſe of a bloudy perſecution.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:183673:14"/>And by all this, we may the better interpret that 11 verſe of the 1. chap. of <hi>Malachy</hi> (who flouriſht in the ſecond temple,) The words are, <hi>From the riſing of the ſun, even unto the going down of the ſame, my name shall be great among the Gentiles, and in every place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe shall be offered unto my name, and a pure offering; for my name shall be great among the heathen, ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi> For beſides that the heathens termed the the temple <hi>the houſe of the great God,</hi> (<hi>Ezra</hi> 5.8.) they and their Monarchs, and Emperours, both of <hi>Perſia, Grece,</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> deſired, as we have heard, to have ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and incenſe, offered for them in Gods name.</p>
               <p n="9">9. And let the reader be pleaſed further to obſerve, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> were accuſtomed, not onely to offer up ſacrifices, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God, for the Emperours, their friends, confederates, and allyes, but alſo generally for the whole world. It is the cuſtome (ſaith <hi>Agrippa</hi> to <hi>Caius</hi> according to <hi>Philo</hi> p. 1035.) for the High-prieſt, at the day of attonement, to make a prayer unto God, for all mankind; beſeeching him to adde unto them another year, with bleſſing and peace. The ſame <hi>Philo Iudaeus</hi> in his ſecond book of <hi>Monarchy</hi> ſaith, <hi>The prieſts of other nations pray unto God onely for the welfare of their own particular nations, but our High-prieſt prayes for the happineſſe and proſperity of the whole world.</hi> And in his book of ſacrifices, p. 836. he ſaith, <hi>Some ſacrifices are offered up for our nation, and ſome for all mankind. For the daily ſacrifices, twice a day,</hi> viz. <hi>at morning, and evening, are for the obtaining of thoſe good things, which God the chief good, grants unto them, at thoſe two times of the day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in like manner, <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his ſecond book againſt <hi>Apion</hi> ſaith, <hi>We ſacrifice, and pray unto the Lord, in the firſt place, for the whole world, for their proſperity, and peace, and afterwards more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly for our ſelves, foraſmuch (as we conceive) that prayer which is firſt extended univerſally, and is afterwards put up more particularly, is very much acceptable unto God.</hi> Which words are alſo related by <hi>Euſebius Caeſareenſis,</hi> in his <hi>Praeparatio Evangelica,</hi> lib. 8. cap. 2.</p>
               <p n="10">10. 'Tis true, that no outward materiall glories are perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; and ſo the <hi>temple</hi> had its period, and with the <hi>paſchall lamb,</hi> all other ſacrifices ceaſed: But in their ſtead, we have at this day <hi>prayer,</hi> and as <hi>Hoſeah</hi> ſpeaks Cap. 14.2. For bullocks, we render
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:183673:15"/>the <hi>calves of our lips.</hi> And three times every day, this is our hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupplication, and requeſt to God, <hi>Fill the whole world, O Lord, with thy bleſsings; for all creatures are the works of thy hands; as it is written, the Lord is good to all, and his tender mercies are ever all his works</hi> Pſal. 145.9.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Yea further, we pray for the converſion of the nations, and ſo we ſay in theſe moſt excellent prayers, upon <hi>Roſ a ſana</hi> and the day of attonement, <hi>Our God, and the God of our Fathers, reign thou over the whole world in thy glory; and be thou exalted over all the earth, in thine excellency; cauſe thy influence to deſcend upon all the inhabitants of the world, in the glorious majeſty of thy ſtrength; and let every creature know that thou haſt created him; and let every thing that is formed, underſtand that thou haſt formed it; and let all that have breath in their noſtrills ſay, the Lord God of Iſrael reighneth, and his kingdome is over all dominions.</hi> And again, <hi>Let all the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the earth know, and ſee, that unto thee every knee shall bow, and every tongue ſwear; before thee, O Lord our God, let them bow, and proſtrate themſelves; let them give honour to the honour of thy name, and let them aell take upon them the yoak of thy kingdome,</hi> &amp;c. And again, <hi>Put thy fear, O Lord, our God, upon all thy works, and thy dread upon all that thou haſt created; let all thy works fear thee, and let all creatures bow down before thee and let them all make themſelves one handfull,</hi> (that is, with joynt conſent) <hi>to do thy will with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart.</hi> &amp;c. A moſt worthy imitation of the wiſe King <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> who after he had finiſhed the building of the Temple, in that long prayer <hi>King.</hi> 1.8. was not unmindfull of the Gentiles, but v. 41. he ſaith, <hi>Moreover, concerning a ſtranger, that is not of thy people of Iſrael, but cometh out of a farre country, for thy names ſake, for they shall hear of thy great name, and of thy ſtrong hand, and of thy ſtretched-out arm, when he shall come, and pray towards this houſe, hear thou in heaven thy dwelling place, and do according to all that the ſtranger calleth to thee for, that all people of the earth may know thy name, to fear thee, as do the people of Iſrael, and that they may know that thy name is called upon this houſe which I have builded.</hi> Where it may be obſerved, that when the Iſraelite comes to pray, he ſaith, 29. <hi>and give every man hccsrding to his wayes;</hi> but upon the prayer of a ſtranger, he ſaith, <hi>and do according to all that the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:183673:15"/>calleth to thee for.</hi> And this diſtinction is made to this end, that by the evident, and apparent return, and anſwer of their prayers, all Gentiles might effectually be brought in to the truth, and knowledge, and fear of God, as well as the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Moreover, ſince the holy prophets made prayers, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications for all men, as well for the <hi>nations,</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> how ſhould not we do the ſame, for the nations, among whom we inhabit, as ingaged by a more eſpeciall obligation, for that we live under their favour and protection? In <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 23.7. God commands <hi>Thou shalt not abhorre an Egyptian,</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heavy burthens they afflicted us with, onely <hi>becauſe thou waſt a ſtranger in his land,</hi> becauſe that at the firſt, they entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and received us into their country.</p>
               <p>As on the other ſide, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.11. he ſaith, <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live.</hi> We ought therefore to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate his actions, and not to hate any man, upon the mere account of religion, but onely to pray to the Lord for his converſion; and this alſo, without giving offence, or any kind of moleſtation. To deteſt, or abhorre thoſe, to whom we owe that proſperity which we enjoy, or who endeavour their own ſalvation, is a thing very unworthy, and ill becoming; but to abhorre their vices, and ſins, is not ſo. It was a very excellent obſervation, of a moſt wiſe, and vertuous Lady, <hi>Beruria,</hi> who (as it is recorded in the <hi>Talmud, Berachot</hi> cap. 1. when her husband <hi>R. Meir</hi> was about to pray to God, to deſtroy ſome of his perverſe, and froward neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that had no leſſe grievouſly, then maliciouſly vexed, and moleſted him, gave him this ſeaſonable admonition, that ſuch a thing <hi>ought not to be done in Iſrael; but that he should rather make his prayer, that they might return, and break off their ſinnes by repentance', alledging that text,</hi> Pſal. 104.35. <hi>Let ſsn be conſumed out of the earth;</hi> it is not ſaid <hi>ſinners,</hi> but <hi>ſinnes;</hi> and then <hi>the wicked shall be no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. We have now in this Section ſhewn, that it is a mere calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to imagine, that we <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhould pray to God, ſo as to give an offence to the Chriſtians, or cauſe ſcandall, by any thing in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:183673:16"/>our prayers, unleſſe it be that we are not Chriſtians. we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to the contrary, how we daily pray for them. As alſo that during the temple, we offered up ſacrifices, for nations confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with us, and how all Emperours deſired this. Yea, and we offered ſacrifices, not onely for particular princes, but for all mankind in generall. How, ſince ſacrifices ceaſed, with the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, we at this day, do the ſame in our prayers, and how we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God for their ſalvation, without giving any ſcandall, or offence in reſpect of religion; and how we think our ſelves obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to perform all this, by the ſacred Scripture. By all which layed together, I hope I have ſufficiently evidenced the truth, of that I have aſſerted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>THE FOURTH SECTION.</head>
               <p>BY conſequence, the accuſation of <hi>Buxtorphius,</hi> in his <hi>Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theca Rabbinorum,</hi> can have no appearance of truth, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that which he puts upon us, <hi>viz.</hi> that we are <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> I will ſet down the Prayer it ſelf.</p>
               <q>We are bound to praiſe the Lord of all things; to magnifie him, who made the world, for that he hath not made us, as the Nations of the earth; nor hath he placed us as the families of the earth; nor hath he made our condition like unto theirs, nor our lot, according to all their multitude. For they humble themſelves to things of no worth, and vanity, and make their prayers to gods that cannot ſave them; but we worſhip before the King of kings, that is holy, and bleſſed; that ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth the Heavens, and framed the Earth; the ſeat of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is in heaven above, and his divine ſtrength in the higheſt of the Heavens; He is our God, and there is no other; He is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, our King, and beſides him, there is no other; as it is wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Law. And know this day, and return into thine own heart, becauſe the Lord is God, in Heaven above, and upon the Earth beneath, there is no other.</q>
               <p>Truly, in my opinion, it is a very ſhort, and moſt excellent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:183673:16"/>prayer, and worthy of commendation. The <hi>Sultan Selim,</hi> that famous conquerour, and Emperour of the <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> made ſo much account of it, that he commanded his Doctor <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Amon,</hi> (who tranſlated the <hi>Pentateuch</hi> into the <hi>Arabian</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> languages) that he ſhould tranſlate our prayers. And when he had delivered them to him in the <hi>Turkish</hi> Tongue, he ſaid to him, what need is there of ſo long prayers? truly this one might ſuffice, he did ſo highly eſteem and value it. This is like an other prayer which was made at that time. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Bleſſed be our God, who created us for his honour, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated us from thoſe that are in errours, and gave unto us a Law of truth, and planted amongſt us eternall life. Let him open our hearts in his law, and put his love in our hearts, and his fear, to do his will, and to ſerve him with a perfect heart, that we may not labour in vain, nor beget children of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Let it be thy will, O Lord our God, and God of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that we may keep thy ſtatutes, and thy laws in this world, and may deſerve, and live, and inherit well, and that we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the bleſſing of the world to come, that ſo we may ſing to thy honour, without ceaſing. O Lord my God, I will praiſe thee for ever.</q>
               <p>But neither the one, nor the other is a <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> or maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt any other Gods, for theſe reaſons following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is not the manner of the <hi>Iewes</hi> by their law to curſe other gods by name, though they be of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> So in <hi>Exod.</hi> cap. 22.27. <hi>Thou shalt not revile the Gods.</hi> Heb. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is <hi>Gods,</hi> or God, as <hi>Philo Iudaeus in libro de Monarchiâ,</hi> doth interpret, and not Judges, as <hi>Onkelus</hi> and <hi>Ionathan</hi> tranſlate in their <hi>Chald.</hi> Paraphr. Where <hi>Philo</hi> addes this reaſon, which is, leſt they hearing their own Gods blaſphemed, ſhould in a revengefull way of reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, blaſpheme the true God of Iſrael. And we have examples enough, how the idolatrous heathen uſed to revile, and defame each others Gods, both in <hi>Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Iuvenal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in that ſenſe <hi>Flavius Joſephus</hi> in his book written againſt <hi>Apion,</hi> ſaith theſe words: <q>As it is our practiſe to obſerve our own, and not to accuſe, or revile others; ſo neither may we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride, or blaſpeeme thoſe, which others account to be Gods.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:183673:17"/>Our Law-giver plainly forbad us that, by reaſon of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, Gods.</q> According to this, by our own religion, we dare not do that which <hi>Buxtorfius</hi> chargeth us with. And upon this account the Talmudiſts tell us, that we ought to honour, and reverence, not onely the Kings of Iſrael, but all kings, princes, and governours, in generall, foraſmuch as the holy Scripture gives them the ſtile of gods, in reſpect of the dignity of their office.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The time wherein theſe, as alſo the other prayers were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and ordered, was in the dayes of <hi>Ezras,</hi> who, with 120 men, amongſt whom were three Prophets, <hi>Haggai, Zechary, Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> compoſed them, as we have it in the <hi>Talmud.</hi> Wherefore he cannot ſay, that there is any thing intended againſt honour, or reverence of Chriſt, who was not born till many yeares after.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſince that calumny was firſt raiſed, (thouh that was ſpoken of the Gentiles, and their vain gods, <hi>humbling themſelves to things of no worth, and vanity</hi>) becauſe they deſire to decline, and avoid the leaſt occaſion of ſcandall, and offence, have left off to print that line, and do not in ſome books print any part thereof. As <hi>John Hoornbeek</hi> alſo witneſſes, in his fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Prolegomena,</hi> and <hi>William Dorſtius,</hi> in his obſervations upon R. <hi>David Gawz,</hi> p. 269. and <hi>Buxtorf</hi> in his book of <hi>Abbreviatures.</hi> And perhaps it will be worthy our obſervation, that all theſe three witneſſes ſay, that it was firſt made known to them, by one <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Margarita,</hi> who was a <hi>Iew,</hi> converted to the Chriſtian ſaith. That this part of the prayer was intended <hi>Contra idola Papatus,</hi> againſt the <hi>Popish idols,</hi> which they therefore, as by a neceſſary conſequence, interpret, as againſt <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but how juſtly, let the unprejudiced and unbiaſed reader judge.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If this be ſo, how can it be thought, that in their <hi>Synagogues,</hi> they name him with ſcornfull ſpitting, (farre be it from us.) The Nation of the <hi>Iewes</hi> is <hi>wiſe, and ingenius.</hi> So ſaid the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> cap. 4.6. <hi>The Nations shall ſay, ſurely this is a wiſe, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding people.</hi> Therefore, how can it be ſuppoſed, that they ſhould be ſo bruitiſh in a ſtrange land, when their Religion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth not upon it? Certainly, it is much contrary to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we ſpake of, to ſhew any reſemblance of ſcorn. There was
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:183673:17"/>never any ſuch thing done, (as it is well known) in <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> where ordinarily the <hi>Synagogues</hi> are full of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> which with great attention, ſtand conſidering, and weighing all their actions, and motions. And truly they ſhould have found great occaſion to find fault withall, if that were ſo. But never was any man heard thus to calumniate us, where ever we dwell and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite, which is a reaſon ſufficiently valid, to clear us. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I ſuppoſe, that I have ſufficiently informed you, concerning our prayers, in which we purpoſe nothing, but to praiſe God, and to ask ſpirituall, and temporall bleſſings, and by our ſervice, and worſhip, implore the divine benevolence, protection, and defence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>THE FIFTH SECTION.</head>
               <p>BUt forraſmuch as it is reported, that we draw, and ſeduce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to our religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Never unto this day, in any part hath this been ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, where the <hi>Iewes</hi> are diſperſëd; nor can it find place here. Truly, I have held friendſhip with many great men, and the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, and moſt eminent of all <hi>Europe;</hi> and alſo they came to ſee me, from many places, at my houſe, and I had many friendly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes with them, yet did not this give occaſion to make us ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of any ſuch things. Yea, <hi>Gaſpar Barleus,</hi> the <hi>Virgill</hi> of our time, and many others, have written many verſes in my commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, which I mention not, for vain glory (farre be it) but for vindication of my innocent repute.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By our rituall books we are clear of this ſeducing. For if any man offer to become a <hi>Iew,</hi> of what Nation ſoever he be, before we receive him, and admit him as a member of our Synagogue, we are bound to conſider, whether he be moved by neceſſity to do it, or if it be not for that he is in love with ſome of our nation, or for any other worldly reſpect. And when we find no reaſon to ſuſpect him, we have yet another obligation upon us, which is, to let him know the penalties he ſubjects himſelf unto, if he breaketh the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:183673:18"/>Sabbath, or eateth bloud, or fat, which is forbidden <hi>Levit.</hi> 3.17. or diſannulleth any precept of the Law, as may be ſeen in the <hi>Targum</hi> upon <hi>Ruth.</hi> And if he ſhew himſelf conſtant, and zealous, then is he admitted and protected. Wherefore we do not ſeduce any one, but contrarily, avoid diſputing with men, concerning religion, not for want of charity, but that we may as farre as it is poſſible, avoid ſcandall, and hate; and for this cauſe we refuſe to circumciſe them that come to us, becauſe we will give no offence. Yea, I have known ſome, that for this cauſe have circumciſed themſelves. And if <hi>Ferdinand</hi> and <hi>Iſabella,</hi> King and Queen of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile</hi> did make an order to expell the <hi>Iewes,</hi> becauſe they ſeduced many Chriſtians, and ſome of the Nobility to become <hi>Iewes,</hi> this was but a pretence, and colour for their tyranny, and onely, as it is well known, having no other thing to object againſt us. Truly, I do much commend that opinion, not onely of <hi>Oſorius, de rebus Immanuelis,</hi> but of our <hi>Flavius Ioſephus,</hi> the moſt famous of all Hiſtorians, which he relates in his hiſtory of his own Life.</p>
               <q>At that time (ſaith he) there came unto me, two Noble men, of the <hi>Trachomites,</hi> ſubjects of the king; bringing with them horſemen, with arms, and money. Theſe, when the <hi>Iewes</hi> would compell to be circumciſed, if they would live amongſt them; I would not ſuffer them to trouble them; maintaining that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ought to ſerve God, of his own free will, and not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thereto by others. For, ſhould we do this thing (ſaith he) it might make them repent, that ever they fled unto us. And ſo perſwading the multitude, I did abundantly afford unto theſe men, their food, according to their diet.</q>
               <p>Truly, this was an action worthy or a noble, and wiſe man, and worthy of imitation, for defending common liberty, leaving the judgement, and determination to God alone. The <hi>Spanish In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions,</hi> with all their torments, and cruelties, cannot make any <hi>Iew,</hi> that falls into their power, become a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> For unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable beaſts are taught by blowes, but men are taught by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Nor are men perſwaded to other opinions, by torments, but rather, on the contrary, they become more firm, and conſtant in their Tenet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:183673:18"/>
               <head>THE SIXTH SECTION.</head>
               <p>HAving thus diſcuſſed the main exceptions, I will now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſmaller matters, though leſſe pertaining to my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, that is to buſineſſe of <hi>Merchandiſe.</hi> Some ſay, that if the <hi>Iewes</hi> come to dwell here, they will draw unto themſelves the whole Negotiation, to the great damage of the naturall Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants. I anſwer, that it hath been my opinion alwayes, (with ſubmiſſion to better judgements) that it can be no prejudice at all to the Engliſh Nation: becauſe, principally in tranſporting their goods, they would gain much, by reaſon of the publick pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of cuſtomes, exciſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, they would alwayes bring profit to the people of the land, as well in buying of commodities, which they would tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to other places, as in thoſe they would trade in here. And if by accident, any particular perſon ſhould loſe by it, by bringing down the price of ſuch a commodity, being diſperſed into many hands; yet by that means the Commonwealth would gain in buying cheaper, and procuring it at a leſſer rate.</p>
               <p>Yea, great emolument would grow to the naturall Inhabitants, as well in the ſale of all proviſion, as in all things elſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the ornaments of the body. Yea, and the native Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks alſo would gain by it, (there being rarely found among us, any man that uſeth any ſuch art.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. Adde to this, that as our nation hath ſailed into almoſt all parts of the world, ſo they are alwayes herein profitable to a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in a readineſſe to give their opinions, in favour of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple amongſt whom they live. Beſide that, all ſtrangers do bring in new merchandiſes, together with the knowledge of thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Countries wherein they were born.</p>
               <p>And this is ſo farre from damnifying the natives, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces much to their advantage; becauſe they bring from their countryes new commodities, with new knowledge. For the great Work-Maſter, and <hi>Creatour</hi> of all things, to the end, to make
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:183673:19"/>commerce in the earth, gave not to every place all things, but hath parted his benefits amongſt them; by which way, he hath made them all wanting the help of others. This may be ſeen in <hi>England,</hi> which being one of the moſt plentifull countries that are in the world, yet wanteth divers things for <hi>shipping;</hi> as alſo, wine, oyl, figs, almonds, raiſins, and and all the drougs of <hi>India,</hi> things ſo neceſſary for the <hi>life of man.</hi> And beſides, they want many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commodities, which are abundant in other countries, with more knowledge of them; though it be true, that in my opinion, there is not in the world, a more underſtanding people, for moſt Navigations, and more capable of all Negotiation, then the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> Nation are.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Farther, there may be companies made of the natives; and ſtrangers, (where they are more acquainted) or elſe Factors. All which, if I be not deceived, will amount to the profit of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives. For which, many reaſons may be brought, though I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend them, having alwayes lived a ſedentary life, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying my ſelf to my ſtudies, which are farre remote from things of that nature.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nor can it be juſtly objected againſt our Nation, that they are deceivers; becauſe the generality cannot in any rationall way, be condemned for ſome particulars. I cannot excuſe them all, nor do I think, but there may be ſome deceivers amongſt them, as well as amongſt all other nations and people, becauſe poverty bringeth baſeneſſe along with it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But if we look to that which we ought by our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the morall precept of the Decalogue, <hi>Thou shalt not ſteal,</hi> it belongs in common to all <hi>Iewes,</hi> towards all <hi>Gentiles.</hi> As may be ſeen in Rab. <hi>Moſes</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Tract, <hi>Geneba,</hi> cap. 1. and <hi>Gazela.</hi> cap. 1. <hi>It is a ſinne,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to rob any man, though he be a Gentile.</hi> Nor can that be alledged out of the ſacred Hiſtory, concerning the jewells and houſhold ſtuff, of which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſpoiled the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> as I have heard it ſometimes alledged by ſome, to ſome men; becauſe that was a particular diſpenſation, and a divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept for that time. So it is recorded in the <hi>Talmud,</hi> in the <hi>Tract of the Sanhedrim,</hi> cap. 11. that in the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, thoſe of <hi>Alexandria</hi> accuſed the <hi>Iewes</hi> for being thieves, and they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:183673:19"/>demanded reſtitution of their goods. But <hi>Guebia Ben Peſria</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them, our Fathers went down into <hi>Egypt</hi> but ſeventy ſouls, there they grew a numerous nation, above 60000. and ſerved them in baſe offices, for the ſpace of 210 yeares, according to this, pay us for our labour, and make the accounts even, and you ſhall ſee you are yet much in our debt. The reaſon ſatisfied <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> and he acquitted them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. By conſequence, the <hi>Iewes</hi> are bound not to defraud, nor abuſe in their accounts, negotiation, or reckonings, any man whatſoever, as it may be ſeen expreſly in R. <hi>Moſes</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and R. <hi>Moſeth de Koſi</hi> in <hi>Samag.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Yea, they farther ſay, that by reſtitutions, there is a reſult to the praiſe of God, and the ſacred Law. whence that holy, and wiſe man, R. <hi>Simeon Ben Satah,</hi> having bought an aſſe of a Gentile, the head ſtall whereof was a jewell of great value, which the owner knew not of, afterwards he found it, and freely, and for nothing, he reſtored it to the ſeller, that knew not of it, ſaying, I bought the aſſe, but not the jewell. Whence there did accrue honour to God, and his Law and to the nation of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> as <hi>Midras Raba</hi> reports in <hi>Paraſot Hekel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. After the ſame manner they command, that the oath which they ſhall make to any other nation, muſt be with truth, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and muſt be kept in every particular. And for proof there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they quote the hiſtory of <hi>Zedekias,</hi> whom God puniſhed, and deprived of his kingdome, becauſe he kept not his word, and <hi>oath,</hi> made to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, in the name of God,</hi> though he were a <hi>Gentile,</hi> as it is ſaid, 2 of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> cap. 36.13. <hi>And he alſo rebelled againſt Nebuchadnezzar, who made him ſwear by God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Theſe are the laws and obligations which the <hi>Iewes</hi> hold. So that the Law that forbids the <hi>Iewes</hi> to <hi>kill</hi> any <hi>Gentiles,</hi> forbids them alſo to <hi>ſteal</hi> from them. Yet every one muſt look to it, for the world is full of fraud in all Nations. I remember a pretty ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of what paſſed in <hi>Morocco,</hi> in the Court of the king of <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tania.</hi> There was a <hi>Iew</hi> that had a ſort of falſe ſtones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — He making a truck with a <hi>Portugal</hi> Chriſtian, for ſome Verdigreaſe that he had, which was much ſofiſticated, (as they are wont to do there) being all falſified with Earth; one of the <hi>Portugals</hi> friends
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:183673:20"/>laughed at him, ſaying, the <hi>Iew</hi> fitted thee well; he anſwered, If the <hi>Iew</hi> hath ſtoned me, I have buried him. And ſo they ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily mock one another.</p>
               <p>This I can affirm, that many of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> becauſe they would not break with other mens goods, were very poor at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> lived very poorly, and thoſe that did break with other mens goods by neceſſity, became ſo much the more miſerable, that they were forced to live on almes.</p>
               <p>And whereas in the time of K. <hi>Edward</hi> 1. the <hi>Iewes</hi> were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of clipping the Kings coin; it appears that this accuſation drew its originall mainly from the ſuſpicion and hatred the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians bare againſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> as appeares in the ſtory, as it is ſet forth by Mr. <hi>Prynne, In his ſecond part of a Short Demurrer to the Iewes</hi> &amp;c. p. 82. where quoting <hi>Clauſ.</hi> 7. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 7. <hi>De fine recipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo à Iudaeis,</hi> brings in the King, writing to his Judges in Latine, in theſe words. <hi>Rex dilectis, &amp; fidelibus ſuis</hi> Stephano de Penteceſter, Waltero de Helyn. <hi>&amp;</hi> Th. de Cobham <hi>Iuſticiariis ad placita tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsionis monetae audienda, ſalutem. Quia omnes</hi> Judaei <hi>nuper rectati, &amp; per certam ſuſpicionem indictati de retonſura monetae noſtrae, &amp; inde convicti cum ultimo ſupplicio puniuntur; &amp; quidam eorum eadem occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, omnia bona, &amp; catalla ſua ſatisfecerunt, &amp; in priſona noſtra liberabantur, in eadem ad voluntatem noſtram detinendi. Et cum accepimus, quod plures Chriſtiani. ob ODIVM</hi> Judaeorum, <hi>propter diſcrepantiam fidei Chriſtianae, &amp; ritus</hi> Judaeorum, <hi>&amp; diverſa gratia minus per ipſos</hi> Judaeos <hi>Chriſtianis hactenus illata, poſtquam Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeos nondum rectatos in indictatos de tranſgreſsione monetae, per levas, &amp; voluntarias accuſationes accuſare, &amp; indictare de die in diem nituntur, &amp; proponunt, imponendas eis ad terrorem ipſorum, quod de ejuſmodi tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsione culpabiles exiſtunt ſuper ipſos</hi> Judaeos <hi>faciendae, &amp; ſic per mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas hujuſmodi accuſationis, ipſis</hi> Judaeos <hi>metu incutiant, &amp; pecuniam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor queant ab eiſdem; Ita quod ipſi</hi> Judaei <hi>ſuper hoc, ad legem ſuam ſaepe ponuntur in vitae ſuae periculum manifeſtum. Volumus quod omnes</hi> Judaei <hi>qui ante primum diem</hi> Maii <hi>proximo praeterit, indictati, velper certam ſuſpicionem rectati non fuerunt de tranſgreſsione monetae predictae; &amp; qui facere voluerint finem juxta diſcretionem Veſtram, ad opus noſtrum facere pro ſic, quod non occaſiorentur, &amp;c. hujuſmodi tranſgreſsionibus factis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te primum diem</hi> Maii <hi>propter novas accuſationes Chriſtianorum poſt eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:183673:20"/>diem inde factas non molestentur, ſed pacem inde habeant in futurum. Proviſo, quod</hi> Judaei <hi>indictati, vel per certam ſuſpicionem, rectati de bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi tranſgreſsione ante praedictum diem</hi> Maii, <hi>Iudicium ſubeant coram vobis, juxta form am prius inde ordinatam &amp; proviſam. Et ideo vobis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neamus, quod fines hujuſmodi capiatis, &amp; praemiſſa fieri, &amp; obſervari fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatis in forma praedicto. Teste Rege apud</hi> Cantuar. 8. <hi>die</hi> Maii.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>THE SEVENTH SECTION.</head>
               <p>ANd now by this time, I preſume (moſt noble Sir) I may have given abundant ſatisfaction, (ſo farre as the nature of an epiſtle will permit) to all your objections, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving juſt ground of offence, or ſcandall to any. And foraſmuch as you are further deſirous to know ſomewhat, concerning the ſtate of this my expedition, and negotiation at preſent, I ſhall now onely ſay, and that briefly, that the communication and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence I have held, for ſome yeares ſince, with ſome eminent perſons of <hi>England,</hi> was the firſt originall of my undertaking this deſign. For I alwayes found by them, a great probability of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining what I now requeſt; whilſt they affirmed, that at this time the minds of men ſtood very well affected towards us; and that our entrance into this Iſland, would be very acceptable, and well-pleaſing unto them. And from this beginning ſprang up in me a ſemblable affection, and deſire of obtaining this purpoſe. For, for ſeven yeares on this behalf, I have endeavoured, and ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, by letters, and other means, without any intervall. For I conceived, that our univerſall diſperſion was a neceſſary circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to be fulfilled, before all that ſhall be accompliſhed which the Lord hath promiſed to the people of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> concerning their reſtauration, and their returning again into their own land, according to thoſe words <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7. <hi>When he shall have accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſcatter the power of the holy people, all theſe things shall be finished.</hi> As alſo, that this our ſcattering, by little, and little, ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all people, from the <hi>one end of the earth even unto the other;</hi> as it is written <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.64. I conceived that by the <hi>end of the earth</hi> might be underſtood this <hi>Iſland.</hi> And I knew not, but that the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:183673:21"/>Lord who often works by naturall meanes, might have deſign'd, and made choice of me, for the brſnging about this work. With theſe propoſalls therefore, I applyed my ſelf, in all zealous affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the <hi>English Nation,</hi> congratulating their glorious liberty which at this day they enjoy, together with their proſperous peace. And I entituled my book named <hi>The hope of Iſrael,</hi> to the firſt Parliament, and the Council of State. And withall decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my intentions. In order to which they ſent me a very favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able paſſe-port. Afterwards I directed my ſelf to the ſecond, and they alſo ſent me another. But at that juncture of time my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming was not preſently performed, for that my kindred and friends, conſidering the checquered, and interwoven viciſſitudes, and turns of things here below, embracing me, with preſſing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, earneſtly requeſted me not to part from them, and would not give over, till their love conſtrained me to promiſe, that I would yet a while ſtay with them. But notwithſtanding all this, I could not be at quiet in my mind, (I know not but that it might be through ſome particular divine providence) till I had anew made my humble addreſſes to his Highneſſe the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector (whom God preſerve.) And finding that my coming over would not be altogether unwelcome to him, with thoſe great hopes which I conceived, I joyfully took my leave of my houſe, my friends, my kindred, all my advantages there, and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try wherein I have lived all my life time, under the benign prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and favour of the Lords, the States Generall, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of <hi>Amſterdam; in fine</hi> (I ſay) I parted with them all, and took my voyage for <hi>England.</hi> Where, after my arrivall, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courteouſly received, and treated with much reſpect, I preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his moſt Serene Highneſſe, a petition, and ſome deſires, which for the moſt part, were written to me by my brethren the <hi>Iewes,</hi> from ſeverall parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> as your worſhip may better underſtand by former relations. Whereupon it pleaſed his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to convene an Aſſembly at <hi>White hall,</hi> of Divines, Lawyers, and Merchants, of different perſwaſions, and opinions. Whereby mens judgements, and ſentences were different. Inſomuch, that as yet, we have had no finall determination from his moſt Serene Highneſſe. Wherefore thoſe few <hi>Iewes</hi> that were here, deſpairing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:183673:21"/>of our expected ſucceſſe, departed hence. And others who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to come hither, have quitted their hopes, and betaken them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſome to <hi>Italy,</hi> ſome to <hi>Geneva,</hi> where that Commonwealth hath at this time, moſt freely granted them many, and great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges.</p>
               <p>Now, O moſt high God, to thee I make my prayer, even to thee, the God of our Fathers. Thou who haſt been pleaſed to ſtile thy ſelf <hi>the keeper of Iſrael;</hi> Thou who haſt graciouſly promiſed, by thy holy Prophet <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> (cap. 31.) <hi>that thou wilt not caſt off all the ſeed of Iſrael, for all the evill that they have done;</hi> thou who by ſo many ſtupendious miracles, didſt bring thy people out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> the land of bondage, and didſt lead them into the <hi>holy land;</hi> graciouſly cauſe thy holy influence to deſcend down into the mind of the Prince, (who for no private intereſt, or reſpect at all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but onely out of commiſeration to our affliction, hath inclined himſelf to protect, and ſhelter us, for which extraordinary hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, neither I my ſelf, nor my nation, can ever expect to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to render him anſwerable, and ſufficient thanks,) and alſo into the minds of his moſt illuſtrious and prudent Council, that they may determine that, which according to thine infinite wiſdome, may be beſt, and moſt expedient for us. For men (O Lord) ſee that which is preſent, but thou in thy omniſciencie ſeeſt that which is afarre off.</p>
               <p>And to the highly honoured nation of <hi>England,</hi> I make my moſt humble requeſt, that they would read over my arguments impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, without prejudice, and devoid of all paſſion, effectually recommending me to their grace and favour, and earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching God that he would be pleaſed to haſten the time promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Zephaniah,</hi> wherein we ſhall all ſerve him <hi>with one conſent,</hi> after the ſame manner, and ſhall be all of the ſame judgement, that as his name is one, ſo his fear may be alſo one, and that we may all ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord, bleſſed forever, and the conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Zion. Amen, and Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my ſtudy, in <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> the 10. in the year from the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation 5416. and in the year, according to the vulgar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="by_the_same_author">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:183673:22"/>
            <p>As to give ſatisfaction to your worſhip, being deſirous to know what books have been written, and printed by me, or elſe are almoſt ready for the preſſe, may you pleaſe to take the names of them in this Catalogue.</p>
            <list>
               <head>A Catalogue of ſuch books as have been published by <hi>Menaſſeh Ben Iſrael,</hi> in <hi>Hebrew.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>NIſmachaim,</hi> four Books, concerning the Immortality of the ſoul, wherein many notable, and pleaſant Queſtions are diſcuſſed, and handled, as may be ſeen by the Arguments of the particular Chapters, prefixed to the book, in <hi>Latine,</hi> dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the then Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pene Rabba,</hi> upon <hi>Rabot,</hi> of the Ancient Rabbins, in <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Spanish.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conciliatoris pars prima in Pentateuchum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De Reſurrectione mortuorum libri tres.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Problemata de creatione.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De termino vitae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De fragilitate humana, ex-lapſu</hi> Adami, <hi>deque divino in bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> opere auxilio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spes Iſraelis.</hi> This is alſo in Engliſh.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Orationes panegyricae, quarum una ad Illuſtriſsimum principem,</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantium, <hi>altera ad ſereniſsimam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reginam</hi> Sueciorum, in <hi>Spanish</hi> onely.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conciliator</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>the ſecond part, upon the firſt Prophets.</item>
                     <item>the third part, upon the later Prophets.</item>
                     <item>the fourth part upon the Hagiographa.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humas,</hi> or the <hi>Pentateuch,</hi> with the ſeverall precepts in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theſoro de los dirim</hi> five books of the rites<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ceremonies of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in two Volumes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humas</hi> the <hi>Pentateuch,</hi> with a commentarie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Piedra pretioſa,</hi> of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar's</hi> image, or the fifth Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Laus or ationes del anno,</hi> the <hi>Iewes</hi> prayers for the whole year, tranſlated out of the originall.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:183673:22"/>
               <head>Books ready for the Preſſe.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>De cultu Imaginum contra Pontificios Latine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sermois,</hi> Sermons in the <hi>Portugal</hi> tongue.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Loci communes Omnium Midraſim,</hi> which contains the divinity of the ancient Rabbins, in <hi>Hebrew.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bibliotheca Rabbinica,</hi> together with the arguments of their books, and my judgement upon their ſeverall editions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Phocylides</hi> in <hi>Spanish</hi> verſe <hi>cum Notis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hippocratis Aphoriſmi</hi> in <hi>Hebrew.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Flavius Ioſephus adverſus Apionem,</hi> in <hi>Hebrew, ejuſdem Monarchia rationis</hi> in <hi>Hebrew.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Refutatio libri cui titulus Praeadamitae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hiſtoria ſive continuatio</hi> Flavii Joſephi <hi>ad haec uſque tempora.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De divinitate legis Moſaicae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De ſcientia Talmudiſtarum, in ſingulis facultatibus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philoſophia Rabbinica.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>De diſciplinis Rabbinorum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nomenclator Hebraius &amp; Arabicus.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I have alſo publiſhed, and printed, with my own preſſe, above 60 other books, amongſt which are many bibles in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Spanish,</hi> with all our <hi>Hebrew</hi> prayers corrected, and diſpoſed in good order.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:183673:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183673:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
